{"tossups": [{"question": "One artwork at this location replaced its central figures with Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin, and the original was made by Dmitri Vrubel. An event at this location concerned the Potsdam Agreement, and was caused by Allan Lightner. Peter Fechter was killed at this location. During a press conference, G\u00fcnter Schabowski (\"GOON-tur SHUH-bau-skee\") said a new (*) travel regulation would be \"effective immediately, without delay,\" leading to this structure\u2019s destruction. My God, Help Me To Survive This Deadly Love was painted on this structure that was crossed at Checkpoint Charlie. Ronald Reagan told Gorbachev (\"GORE-buh-chev\") to tear down, for 10 points, what structure between the East and West parts of its namesake German capital?", "answer": "Berlin Wall", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Berlin Wall</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Berlin Wall"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This work opens on a character who was \u201ctoo drunk to remember to shut the popholes.\u201d One character in this work can\u2019t get past the letter \"D\" while learning the alphabet and dies in a glue factory. Moses talks about the paradise Sugarcandy Mountain in this work. Barley is used to make a certain good after the (*) Seven Commandments are changed to allow alcohol. In this work, the motto, \"I will work harder\" is repeated by Boxer. Squealer attempts to portray Snowball as a traitor in this work. During this work\u2019s Battle of the Windmill, Napoleon directs troops. Sheep drown out protesters by chanting \"Four legs good, two legs bad\" in this work. \"Beasts of England\" is sung in, for 10 points, what George Orwell novella?", "answer": "Animal Farm: a Fairy Story", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Animal Farm: a Fairy Story</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Animal Farm: a Fairy Story"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "NOTE TO PLAYERS: Description acceptable One of these things used its APXS spectrometer to analyze \"Barnacle Bill.\" An object accompanying one of these things was granted an \u201coperations demonstration phase concluding at Wright Brothers Field. Rosalind Franklin is a planned one of these things. One of these things was a part of the Tianwen-1 mission and named (*) Zhurong. InSight attempted to track one of these things. A 2021 mission involving these things landed in Jezero Crater and underwent the \"Seven Minutes of Terror.\" Some of these things descend using the\"sky crane\" system. One of these crafts accompanies the helicopter Ingenuity. For 10 points, name these space exploration crafts, including Perseverance and Curiosity, on the red planet.", "answer": "Mars rovers [accept anything mentioning rovers on Mars; prompt on rovers; prompt on Mars missions with \"What vehicle was being brought to Mars?\"; do NOT accept or prompt on answers mentioning \"landers\"]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Mars rovers</u></b> [accept <b><u>anything mentioning rovers on Mars</u></b>; prompt on <u>rovers</u>; prompt on <u>Mars missions with \"What vehicle was being brought to Mars?</u>; do NOT accept or prompt on answers mentioning \"landers\"]", "acceptable": ["Mars rovers", "anything mentioning rovers on Mars"], "promptable": ["rovers", "Mars missions with \"What vehicle was being brought to Mars?"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This composer rejected the descriptions \"requiem\" or \"memorial\" for one of their pieces, calling it a \"memory space.\" One piece formerly called Fanfare for Great Woods features a woodblock ostinato. One piece by this composer includes a children\u2019s choir and pre-recorded tape, and opens with a child repeating the word \"missing\" while names are read. One opera by this composer includes the aria \"This is prophetic\" and a man arriving on the (*) Spirit of \u201876. In addition to a work commemorating 9/11 victims, this composer wrote an opera with characters like Zhou En-lai and Mao Tse-tung. For 10 points, name this composer of Short Ride in a Fast Machine, On The Transmigration of Souls, and Nixon in China.", "answer": "John Coolidge Adams", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>John Coolidge Adams</u></b>", "acceptable": ["John Coolidge Adams"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The companies Rivian and NIO (\"NEO\") make these products. One of these products has features like \"Sentry Mode\" and \"Dog Mode.\" The \"Gigafactory Texas\" is being built to make these products. The CEO of one company praised the angular design of one of these products since it \"looks like it was made by aliens,\" though its \"armor glass\" cracked during an unveiling ceremony. One of these things held the dummy astronaut \"Starman\" as payload for a (*) Falcon Heavy test flight. To promote these products, Volkswagen jokingly announced that they would change their name to \"Voltswagen.\" The \"Roadster\" and \"Cybertruck\" are examples of, for 10 points, what alternatives to gas-powered automobiles, including the Nissan Leaf and Tesla\u2019s Model S, 3, X, and Y?", "answer": "electric vehicles [accept EVs or electric cars; prompt on cars or vehicles; anti-prompt on specific EV models with \"be less specific, what power source do they use?\"]", "subcategory": "Trash", "category": "Trash", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>electric vehicles</u></b> [accept <b><u>EVs</u></b> or <b><u>electric cars</u></b>; prompt on <u>cars</u> or <u>vehicles</u>; anti-prompt on specific EV models with \"be less specific, what power source do they use?\"]", "acceptable": ["electric vehicles", "EVs", "electric cars"], "promptable": ["cars", "vehicles"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Pierre de Coubertin (\"COO-behr-tahn\") helped organize one of these events. Hungarian and Soviet participants at one of these events met in an incident called \"blood in the water.\" A crime at one of these events, retaliated against in Operation Wrath of God, was committed by the Palestinian group (*) Black September. Richard Jewell discovered Eric Rudolph\u2019s plot to bomb Atlanta\u2019s Centennial Park for the 1996 one of these events. The Munich massacre occurred at one of these events. At one of these events, Jesse Owens won four track gold medals. For 10 points, name these quadrennial international sporting events, at which its namesake \"torch\" is lit at its opening ceremony.", "answer": "Summer Olympic Games [accept 1896 Olympics, 1936 Olympics, 1956 Olympics, 1972 Olympics, 1996 Olympics; do NOT accept or prompt on answers mentioning \"Winter Olympics\"]", "subcategory": "Other History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Summer Olympic Games</u></b> [accept <b><u>1896 Olympics, 1936 Olympics, 1956 Olympics, 1972 Olympics, 1996 Olympics</u></b>; do NOT accept or prompt on answers mentioning \"Winter Olympics\"]", "acceptable": ["Summer Olympic Games", "1896 Olympics, 1936 Olympics, 1956 Olympics, 1972 Olympics, 1996 Olympics"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This thinker rejected an idea put forth by Daniel Brinton and examined how people described one sound in different ways in their article \"On Alternating Sounds.\" When studying immigrants, this thinker disproved the idea that head shape was a racial trait. This thinker developed the idea that cultures cannot be (*) ranked because all people judge the world by their own cultural norms. This man argued that his field should be subdivided into \"physical\" and \"cultural\" forms and include linguistics and archaeology. The ideas of cultural relativism and the four-field approach were developed by this author of The Mind of Primitive Man. For 10 points, name this Columbia anthropology professor and teacher of Zora Neale Hurston and Ruth Benedict.", "answer": "Franz Uri Boas", "subcategory": "Social Science", "category": "Social Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Franz Uri Boas</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Franz Uri Boas"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A poem titled for this character describes them as \"a master from Deutschland\" and opens \"Black milk of morning.\" That poem is by Paul Celan (\"SEH-luhn\"). \" This figure gambles with another figure who has skin \"as white as leprosy\" in \"The Rime of the Ancient Mariner.\" An e.e. cummings poem asks this character \"how do you like your blue-eyed boy.\u201d One sonnet describes this figure as \"mighty and (*) dreadful,\" and calls them \"slave to fate, chance, kings, and desperate men.\" The narrator of another poem rides with Immortality and this figure in a carriage. A John Donne poem tells this figure to \"be not proud.\" For 10 points, name this character who, in another poem, \"kindly stops\" for Emily Dickinson.", "answer": "death [accept Deathfugue or Todesfuge, accept mister death, accept Death, Be Not Proud, accept Because I Could Not Stop for Death, do NOT accept or prompt on \"Life-in-Death\"]", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>death</u></b> [accept <b><u>Deathfugue</u></b> or <b><u>Todesfuge,</u></b> or <b><u>mister death,</u></b> or <b><u>Death, Be Not Proud,</u></b> or <b><u>Because I Could Not Stop for Death, do NOT</u></b> or <b><u>or prompt on \"Life-in-Death</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["death", "Deathfugue", "Todesfuge,", "mister death,", "Death, Be Not Proud,", "Because I Could Not Stop for Death, do NOT", "or prompt on \"Life-in-Death"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "Internal and external self-stresses in one type of this substance causes its breaking pattern to be square-like. At the transition point named for this material, brittle substances start to become more viscous and rubber-like. A type of this substance forms naturally, following volcanic eruptions, when (*) lava cools into obsidian. In a technique for creating this substance, its solid, brittle form is placed on the end of a blowing tube, super-heated to its liquid phase, then cooled down to form it. Boron trioxide and silica are the main components of the \"Pyrex\" type of this substance. The \"tempered\" variety of this substance is used in phone screens. For 10 points, name this amorphous, transparent material used in flasks and windows.", "answer": "glass [accept pyrex glass, or tempered glass]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>glass</u></b> [accept <b><u>pyrex glass,</u></b> or <b><u>tempered glass</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["glass", "pyrex glass,", "tempered glass"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "It\u2019s not California, but the Berkeley Pit mine lies in this state\u2019s Silver Bow County and is full of heavily acidic water. A lake in this state, Flathead Lake, lies near this state\u2019s city of Kalispell (\"kah-lih-SPELL\"). Froze-to-Death Mountain is near this state\u2019s highest point, Granite Peak. The Fort Peck dam lies on the Missouri River, which runs through this state\u2019s city of (*) Great Falls. This state, which is the only to border Alberta, has the longest border with Canada. Heavens Peak and Lake MacDonald are near Going-to-the-Sun Road in a national park in this state. Butte, Billings, and Bozeman are cities in, for 10 points, what state that contains Glacier National Park, and its capital, Helena?", "answer": "Montana", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Montana</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Montana"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This leader promoted the ideas that \"Knowledge will be sought throughout the world\" and \"Evil customs of the past shall be broken off.\" This leader, who was targeted by the High Treason Incident, used the slogan \u201cEnrich the country and strengthen the military.\u201d A revolt against this leader as a result of his support of the (*) Charter Oath ended at the Battle of Shiroyama and was led by Saigo Takamori (\"SIGH-go tah-kuh-more-E\"). This emperor promoted faced the Satsuma Rebellion. The Japanese constitution is named informally for this emperor. For 10 points, name this emperor who led a namesake \"restoration.\"", "answer": "Emperor Meiji [accept Meiji the Great or Meiji the Good]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Emperor <b><u>Meiji</u></b> [accept <b><u>Meiji the Great</u></b> or <b><u>Meiji the Good</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Emperor Meiji", "Meiji the Great", "Meiji the Good"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The title object of one of this author\u2019s poems is given to an \"Iron-hearted man-slaying\" character \"Who would not live long\" and depicts \"An artificial wilderness / And a sky like lead.\" In addition to \"The Shield of Achilles,\" this poet wrote \"In Praise of Limestone\" and a poem that describes finding \"What huge imago (\"uh-may-gow\") made / A psychopathic God.\" At the end of that poem, this author hopes to \"Show an affirming flame\" and states \"We must (*) love one another or die.\" This author commands \"Stop all the clocks, cut off the telephone\" in his poem \"Funeral Blues,\" and set his most famous poem \"in one of the dives / On Fifty-second Street.\" For 10 points, name this modernist poet of \"September 1st, 1939.\"", "answer": "Wystan Hugh Auden [or W. H. Auden]", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "Wystan Hugh <b><u>Auden</u></b> [or <b><u>W. H. Auden</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Wystan Hugh Auden", "W. H. Auden"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One candidate in this election lives with fifteen stray cats and beat Ferdinand Mateo in a primary. The non-binary rapper Paperboy Prince ran for one party\u2019s nomination in this election. Jean (\"JOHN\") Kim accused one candidate of sexual assault in a primary to this election, that candidate was Scott Stringer (\"stryn-jer\"). The Republican nominee in this election founded the Guardian Angels. 135,000 (*) test votes were accidentally counted in a primary to this election. Because of ranked-choice voting in the Democratic primary to this election, an alliance between Kathryn Garcia and Andrew Yang was formed to oppose Eric Adams. Due to term limits, Bill de Blasio cannot run in, for 10 points, what election for the leader of a city with boroughs such as Queens and Brooklyn?", "answer": "2021 New York City mayoral election [accept \"NYC\" in place of \"New York City\"; accept any answer mentioning an election for Mayor of New York City; prompt on partial answers; anti-prompt on 2021 New York City Democratic primary or 2021 New York City Republican primary]", "subcategory": "Current Events", "category": "Current Events", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>2021 New York City mayoral election</u></b> [accept <b><u>NYC\" in place of \"New York City</u></b>; accept <b><u>any answer mentioning an election for Mayor of New York City</u></b>; prompt on <u>partial answers</u>; anti-prompt on 2021 New York City Democratic primary or 2021 New York City Republican primary]", "acceptable": ["2021 New York City mayoral election", "NYC\" in place of \"New York City", "any answer mentioning an election for Mayor of New York City"], "promptable": ["partial answers"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "A parody of this painting shows two overturned white plastic chairs by the central location and a man in Union Jack boxers pointing at a broken window. Banksy and Gottfried Helnwein (\"got-freed heln-when\") parodied this piece, which the artist described as \"unconsciously.. the loneliness of a large city.\" A golden (*) knobless door is the only point of entry in this painting, which depicts a cherry-wood counter holding the drinks of a woman in a red blouse sitting near two men and a waiter. A sign in this painting depicts an ad for five-cent \"Phillies\" cigars. For 10 points, name this painting which depicts nighttime patrons at a diner by Edward Hopper.", "answer": "Nighthawks", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Nighthawks</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Nighthawks"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The \"hop diffusion\" motion of these compounds is explained by interactions with an actin skeleton in the fences-and-pickets model. A serine-containing example of these compounds called PS aids in efferocytosis (\"F-ear-oh-cye-toe-sis\") signaling when it\u2019s externalized. Flippases and floppases can facilitate transport of these compounds between (*) leaflets. The lateral movement of these compounds is described by the fluid mosaic model. These compounds have hydrophilic heads and pairs of hydrophobic fatty-acid tails. For 10 points, name these compounds that make up a bilayer in the cell membrane.", "answer": "phospholipids [accept anything indicating a cell membrane component before mention; prompt on lipids]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>phospholipids</u></b> [accept <b><u>anything indicating a cell membrane component</u></b> before mention; prompt on <u>lipids</u>]", "acceptable": ["phospholipids", "anything indicating a cell membrane component"], "promptable": ["lipids"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An eleven-year-old schoolgirl who lived on this country\u2019s island of Wolin found a golden disc that belonged to Viking King Bluetooth. In the Old Town of this country\u2019s capital, a statue of a young boy, the \"Little Insurrectionist,\" is holding a submachine gun. It\u2019s not Slovakia, but the highest point in this country, Mount Rysy, is part of the Tatra Mountains. The largest stadium in this country, Stadium Narodowy, sits on the (*) Vistula River, and this country shares the region of Pomerania with Germany. An exclave of Russia, Kaliningrad is sandwiched by this country and Lithuania. A city in this country, Gdansk lies on the Baltic Sea. For 10 points, name this country with a capital at Warsaw.", "answer": "Republic of Poland [accept Polska]", "subcategory": "Geography", "category": "Geography", "answer_formatted": "Republic of <b><u>Poland</u></b> [accept <b><u>Polska</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["Republic of Poland", "Polska"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "On this day, the Kohen Gadol is called upon to perform a series of services. The double-acrostic \"Al Chet\" prayer is read on this holiday. Some observants of this holiday wear a white robe called kittel. Though not Tisha B\u2019Av, this day\u2019s Five Prohibitions include not wearing leather shoes and not using perfumes and lotions. A (*) goat is sacrificed on this day \"for Azazel.\" The blowing of the shofar concludes the closing Ne\u2019ila prayer on this day. The \"all vows\" prayer, or Kol Nidre is chanted on this day, where above a certain age, fasting is required. For 10 points, name this \"Day of Atonement,\" the holiest day of the year in Judaism.", "answer": "Yom Kippur [accept Tosefet Yom Kippur; accept Day of Atonement before mention]", "subcategory": "Religion", "category": "Religion", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Yom Kippur</u></b> [accept <b><u>Tosefet Yom Kippur</u></b>; accept <b><u>Day of Atonement</u></b> before mention]", "acceptable": ["Yom Kippur", "Tosefet Yom Kippur", "Day of Atonement"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In a photograph, Bill and Gayle Newman were shown shielding their children\u2019s eyes after this event. J.D. Tippit was killed after this event, which saw the perpetrator\u2019s arrest in a movie theater. Arlen Specter helped formulate the \"magic bullet theory\" for this event. This event was captured by the (*) Zapruder film, and Jack Ruby killed the perpetrator of this event. The Warren Commission investigated theories around this event, like if Louie Witt, the \"umbrella man\" perpetrated this event, or if the \"lone gunman\" had an accomplice on a \"grassy knoll.\" A presidential motorcade was shot in Dallas\u2019 Dealey Plaza during, for 10 points, what November 1963 event where Lee Harvey Oswald killed the 35th president?", "answer": "assassination of John Fitzgerald Kennedy [accept reasonable equivalents like death of John Fitzgerald Kennedy; accept answers replacing \"Kennedy\" with \"JFK\"; prompt on answers only mentioning \"Kennedy\"]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>assassination of John Fitzgerald Kennedy</u></b> [accept <b><u>reasonable equivalents like death of John Fitzgerald Kennedy</u></b>; accept <b><u>answers replacing \"Kennedy\" with \"JFK</u></b>; prompt on <u>answers only mentioning \"Kennedy</u>]", "acceptable": ["assassination of John Fitzgerald Kennedy", "reasonable equivalents like death of John Fitzgerald Kennedy", "answers replacing \"Kennedy\" with \"JFK"], "promptable": ["answers only mentioning \"Kennedy"], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In this play, one character plays the guitar while claiming it\u2019s a mandoline. Another character in this play congratulates a bookcase for existing for 100 years, and frequently narrates games of air-billiards in the middle of conversations. Nicknames used in this play include \"Little Cucumber,\" \"Two-and-twenty troubles,\" and (*) \"Eternal student.\" In this play, Lubov gives a tramp a gold coin, instead of the 30 copeks he had asked for, and later weeps as Lopakhin discusses having won an auction. This play concludes with the old footman Fiers (\u201cFEARZ\u201d) locked in an estate on the title property. For 10 points, name this Chekhov play that ends with the sound of an ax chopping down trees.", "answer": "The Cherry Orchard", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>The Cherry Orchard</u></b>", "acceptable": ["The Cherry Orchard"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This quantity is given by surface gravity over two pi for black holes. Systems in population inversion have a negative value for this quantity. The probability of being in a given state is proportional to the negative exponential of the state\u2019s energy over this quantity times Boltzmann\u2019s constant. Ferromagnetism is lost when this quantity is above the (*) Curie point. Phase diagrams most typically plot pressure against this quantity. This quantity is proportional to the average translational kinetic energy of particles in a gas, and its theoretical lower limit is absolute zero. For 10 points, name this quantity measured in Kelvin.", "answer": "temperature [or absolute temperature; accept T]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>temperature</u></b> [or <b><u>absolute temperature</u></b>; accept <b><u>T</u></b>]", "acceptable": ["temperature", "absolute temperature", "T"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}], "bonuses": []}